Inventory of the Richard Wirthlin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Richard Wirthlin papers
1967-2005
2007C27
Hoover Institution Archives
248 cubic foot boxes, 2 oversize boxes (310.8 linear feet)
Polling data, reports, studies, correspondence, speeches, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to American public opinion on domestic political and foreign policy issues. Includes polls conducted on behalf of Ronald Reagan in conjunction with his campaigns for governor of California and president of the United States, as well as polling during his presidency.
Wirthlin, Richard
Access
Collection is mainly stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007, with additional increments through 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Ronald Reagan subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Citizens for Reagan records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
Richard Bitner Wirthlin was born in Salt Lake City on March 15, 1931, the son of Joseph L. and Madeline Bitner Wirthlin. He earned his bachelor's and master's degrees at the University of Utah and his Ph.D. at the University of California, Berkeley. Wirthlin noted that he became interested in economics and politics while doing Mormon missionary work in Switzerland and Austria in 1951.
An economist turned political consultant and pollster, Wirthlin began conducting survey research in 1964. Many of his early clients were political candidates in Utah and Arizona, where he taught economics at Brigham Young University and Arizona State University.
Wirthlin's company, originally based in Los Angeles and successively named Decision Making Information, the Wirthlin Group and Wirthlin Worldwide, also did polling for Margaret Thatcher and Barry Goldwater, among other political clients. The company was sold to Harris Interactive in 2004, with Wirthlin serving on its board until retiring in 2007. Wirthlin's companies showed how to integrate different kinds of data - polling, census, political - to measure the electorate's opinions and moods.
Wirthlin first met California Governor Ronald Reagan in 1968, and conducted his first survey for Reagan in that year. He did a number of additional research projects between 1968 and 1976 for Governor Reagan. When Reagan decided to run for the Republican presidential nomination in 1980, he turned to Wirthlin and his company. When Reagan won the White House, Wirthlin moved to Washington, D.C., and continued to provide regular survey research and counsel on strategy and communications through the first term, for the re-election campaign in 1984, and through the second term until Reagan left office in January 1989. It was the most comprehensive program of public opinion research ever undertaken by a president of the United States.
Source:
"Richard Wirthlin, Pollster Who Advised Reagan, Dies at 80," by Adam Clymer, New York Times, March 17, 2011. Accessed: November 11, 2011.
"Background on Wirthlin-Reagan Books," Hoover Institution Archives correspondence with Bryce Bassett, 2002
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers include a significant amount of polling data, reports, and studies, relating to American public opinion on domestic political and foreign policy issues, often political candidates or general mood of the electorate at a particular moment in time during the 1970s and 1980s.
A large portion of the collection is based on political polling studies. The deliverable for each study consisted of computer cross-tabulations of the survey data, and sometimes charts, graphs, and written analysis and interpretation of the survey results. Organized in bound volumes, the books offer a unique snapshot of public opinion on particular topics. Large studies were divided into multiple books, so one project may have 2 or 3 volumes.
Along with overall studies, flash results are documents that contain quick analysis and charts from major national studies. Flash results were prepared quickly after the survey, and given to the client as a "topline result" from the poll, before the full analysis could be prepared and the cross-tabs printed and bound and analyzed.
The books are arranged in the system created by Wirthlin's firm, in a numeric sequence by client, described in detail below. The books are divided into two groups by topic, Reagan Books and Political Polling Books. When an additional increment of materials arrived at the archives at a later date, two more groups were created, Incremental Reagan Books and Incremental Political Polling Books.
In addition to the books, the papers contain Wirthlin's Files, which include correspondence, speeches, memoranda, interview transcripts, calendars, and printed matter, relating to Wirthlin's work, Ronald Reagan, and American public opinion on domestic political and foreign policy issues. Of particular interest is the document Personal and Public Perspectives on the Reagan Presidency, written by Wirthlin in 1991 and found in box 269. The Files contain many similar materials to the books, so researchers should be sure to check both sets of materials for documentation on a particular topic.
Wirthlin File Number System
A numbering system was developed by Wirthlin's firm to keep track of the books on the company shelves and inventories. Most books have the number on the spine of the book. The Hoover Institution Archives has retained this 9-digit system of organization so that all the studies for one client are shelved together, in chronological order. The 9-digit number looks like this: 699-002-056.
The format is DGG-CCC-NNN, where:
D = division of the company that conducted the study. 1 was media, 2 government, 4 marketing, 6 political. Everything in the Hoover Institution Archives collection starts with a 6.
GG = geographic area of the study, where the survey was conducted. Statewide surveys had two digit numbers from 01 (Alabama) through 51 (Wyoming). 98 meant a "regional" survey, something conducted in more than one state, but not nationally. 99 meant a national survey.
CCC = client number within that region and division, assigned sequentially starting with 001
NNN = study number, for that client, within that region and division, assigned sequentially starting with 001
So, 699-002-056 translates to "the 56th study conducted for the company's 2nd national political client."
699-002 is the Republican National Committee, for whom Wirthlin worked before Reagan became president, so the first national Reagan study in 1980 is numbered 699-002-011. Pre-dating that were studies done for "Citizens for Reagan" in 1975, the 7th national political client, hence 699-007. In 1979, Reagan's second run for the nomination was considered by the firm as a new client, so "Reagan for President" became 699-016. It kept that number for Reagan/Bush, and later Reagan/Bush '84. Because each state has its own sequential client numbering system, statewide surveys done for Reagan have a different middle client number in every state. In Alabama, the RNC was 601-006, in Arizona 603-021, and in California 605-067, etc.
Each research project also had a four-digit project number, used internally within the company to keep track of all the phases of the study and the billing. A version number was added because a given project number or file number could have several volumes, sometimes dozens. Many of these books have a book number handwritten on the title page or elsewhere.
Abbreviations
In addition to standard state two-letter postal codes, there are a number of organizations referred to in common abbreviations, including:
Republican National Committee (RNC)
Decision Making Information (DMI)
National Republican Congressional Committee (NRCC)
National Republican Senatorial Committee (NRSC)
Republican Congressional Campaign Committee (RCCC)
Reagan, Ronald.; California--Politics and government--1951-; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Presidents--United States--Election--1984.; Public opinion--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1981-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.
- Reagan Books, 1968-1988 (Box 1-133)
  Arrangement note
  Arranged by file number. Additional fields listing versions and geographic data points available at the Hoover Institution. Key: File number. Client: Title, Dates
  - 601-003-002. Reagan/Bush: Alabama Brushfire Survey, October 13, 1980 - October 14, 1980 (Box 1)
  - 601-006-002. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Alabama, September 8, 1985 - September 10, 1985 (Box 1)
  - 601-006-002. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Alabama, September 8, 1985 - September 10, 1985 (Box 1)
  - 601-006-002. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Alabama, September 8, 1985 - September 10, 1985 (Box 1)
  - 601-006-003. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Alabama, October 12, 1986 - October 13, 1986 (Box 1)
  - 602-003-001. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Alaska Voters, May 31, 1980 - June 2, 1980 (Box 1)
  - 603-020-001. Reagan/Bush '84 Committee: A Statewide Survey of Arizona Voters, February 10, 1984 - February 12, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-001. Governor Ronald Reagan: State Legislature California Statewide, August 21, 1969 - August 28, 1969 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-002. CIS: California Tracking, August 1, 1969 - June 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-002. CIS: Tracking, June 1, 1970 - August 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-007. Governor Ronald Reagan: 2nd California Statewide, February 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-007. Governor Ronald Reagan: 2rd California Statewide, February 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-007. Governor Ronald Reagan: 2rd California Statewide, February 1, 1970 (Box 2)
  - 605-007-008. U.S. Senate: California Statewide, July 1, 1970 - August 1, 1970 (Box 3)
  - 605-007-008. Governor Ronald Reagan: California Statewide, July 1, 1970 - August 1, 1970 (Box 3)
  - 605-007-008. CIS: California Statewide Special Cross, July 1, 1970 - August 1, 1970 (Box 3)
  - 605-007-008.: Third Statewide - Special Mexican-American Breakouts, July 1, 1970 - August 1, 1970 (Box 3)
  - 605-007-011. Governor Ronald Reagan: California Statewide, October 1, 1969 (Box 3)
  - 605-007-011. Governor Ronald Reagan: California Statewide, October 1, 1969 (Box 3)
  - 605-010-002. Governor Ronald Reagan: Special Cross-Tabulations (Box 3)
  - 605-011-001. Southern California Edison: Stoddard Mountain Survey of Public Attitudes Toward Establishment of a Power Plant in Mojave Water District, October 1, 1969 (Box 4)
  - 605-015-014. Citizens for Reagan: California Tracking Studies, May 20, 1976 - June 1, 1976 (Box 4)
  - 605-064-003. Governor Ronald Reagan: A Study of Voter Attitudes in California, August 2, 1974 - August 12, 1974 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-001. RNC: California Impact Study (Box 4)
  - 605-067-004. RNC: A Survey of Voter Attitudes, June 14, 1980 - June 15, 1980 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-005. RNC: California 1st Quarter Report, January 1, 1981 - April 16, 1981 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-006. RNC: A Statewide Survey of California Voters, May 28, 1981 - June 6, 1981 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-007. RNC: California Second Statewide Quarter Report - From "Eagle" Surveys I-X, January 1, 1981 - August 14, 1981 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-008. RNC: 3rd California Statewide Report from 14 National "Eagle" Surveys, January 1, 1981 - October 26, 1981 (Box 4)
  - 605-067-009. RNC: 4th California Statewide Report from 16 National "Eagle" Surveys, January 1, 1981 - December 1, 1981 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-011. RNC: A California Statewide Post-Election Panel Survey, November 10, 1982 - November 16, 1982 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-014. RNC: Voter Attitudes in California from 20 National Surveys, January 1, 1983 - May 1, 1984 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-020. RNC: Survey of Reg. Voters in California, September 22, 1985 - September 24, 1985 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-021. RNC: A Banner Report Based on Merged 1985 Data for California, November 1, 1984 - November 1, 1985 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-022. RNC: Telephone Survey of Registered Voters in California, July 12, 1986 - July 15, 1986 (Box 5)
  - 605-067-023. RNC: Telephone Survey of Registered Voters in California, August 19, 1988 - August 21, 1988 (Box 5)
  - 605-074-001. Citizens for Reagan: A Telephone Survey of Likely Republican Voters in California - Analysis, May 5, 1976 - May 8, 1976 (Box 5)
  - 605-074-002. Citizens for Reagan: California Tracking Studies - Four Waves, May 20, 1976 - June 1, 1976 (Box 5)
  - 605-074-002. Citizens for Reagan: California Tracking Studies - Four Waves, May 20, 1976 - June 1, 1976 (Box 5)
  - 605-123-001. Reagan for President: California Presidential Primary Tracking, May 13, 1980 - June 2, 1980 (Box 5)
  - 605-123-002. Reagan/Bush Committee: California Statewide - Wave 1, August 20, 1980 - August 27, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-002. Reagan/Bush Committee: California Statewide - Wave 1, August 20, 1980 - August 27, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-003. Reagan/Bush: California Statewide Wave II, September 12, 1980 - September 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-003. Reagan/Bush: California Statewide Wave II, September 12, 1980 - September 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 6)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 7, 1980 - October 13, 1980 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-004. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 19, 1980 - October 22, 1980 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-005. Reagan/Bush: A Statewide Survey of Voter Attitudes in California, March 16, 1984 - March 22, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-006. Reagan/Bush '84: A Statewide Telephone Survey of Voters in California, June 12, 1984 - June 16, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-007. Reagan/Bush '84: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in California, August 8, 1984 - August 13, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-008. Reagan/Bush '84: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in California, September 10, 1984 - September 12, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-009. Reagan/Bush '84: Cross sectional Califronia, August 1, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-009. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, September 10, 1984 - September 1, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-010. Reagan/Bush '84: A Brushfire Survey of Registered Voters in California, September 28, 1984 - September 29, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-012. Reagan/Bush: California Statewide Tracking, October 1, 1984 - October 31, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-013. Reagan/Bush: A Brushfire Survey of California Voters, October 17, 1984 - October 17, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-014. Reagan/Bush '84: California Tracking, October 19, 1984 - November 5, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-015. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, October 31, 1984 - November 2, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 605-123-015. Reagan/Bush: California Tracking, November 2, 1984 - November 4, 1984 (Box 7)
  - 606-015-003. RNC: Voters Attitudes in State of Colorado - extracted from 20 national surveys, January 1, 1983 - May 1, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-001. Reagan/Bush Committee: Connecticut Tracking - Wave I, August 19, 1980 - August 21, 1980 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-002. RNC: Connecticut Statewide, September 1, 1980 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-002. Reagan/Bush: Connecticut Statewide - Wave II, September 12, 1980 - September 13, 1980 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-003. RNC: Connecticut Tracking, October 1, 1980 - November 1, 1980 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-003. Reagan/Bush: Connecticut Tracking - 1st Cross-Tabulation Run, October 14, 1980 - November 2, 1980 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-006. Reagan/Bush '84: Connecticut Statewide Tracking, October 11, 1984 - November 4, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-006. Reagan/Bush '84: Connecticut Statewide Tracking, October 11, 1984 - November 4, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-006. Reagan/Bush '84: Connecticut Statewide Tracking, October 11, 1984 - November 4, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-006. Reagan/Bush '84: Connecticut Statewide Tracking, November 1, 1984 - November 4, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 607-014-007. Reagan/Bush '84: Connecticut Tracking, October 23, 1984 - November 5, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 608-002-001. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Voter Attitudes in Delaware, April 28, 1979 - April 28, 1979 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-004. RNC: First Florida Statewide Report Extracted from National "Eagle" Surveys, January 1, 1981 - January 14, 1981 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-005. RNC: Second Florida Statewide Report Extracted from National "Eagle" Surveys, September 1, 1981 - December 1, 1981 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-007. RNC: Voter Attitudes in Florida Extracted from Twenty National Surveys, January 1, 1983 - May 1, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-007. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Florida, June 6, 1984 - June 10, 1984 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-013. RNC: A Banner Based on Merged 1984-1985 Data, November 1, 1984 - November 1, 1985 (Box 8)
  - 610-003-014. RNC: A Statewide Survey Of Voter Attitudes in Florida, December 10, 1985 - December 12, 1985 (Box 9)
  - 610-003-014. RNC: A Statewide Survey Of Voter Attitudes in Florida, December 10, 1985 - December 12, 1985 (Box 9)
  - 610-003-015. RNC: A Telephone Survey of Voter Attitudes in Florida, September 21, 1986 - September 23, 1986 (Box 9)
  - 610-003-016. RNC: Florida Statewide, September 1, 1986 (Box 9)
  - 610-003-016. RNC: Florida Statewide, September 1, 1986 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-001. Citizens for Reagan: Survey of Florida Republicans, December 6, 1975 - December 18, 1975 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-001. Citizens for Reagan: Survey of Florida Republicans, December 6, 1975 - December 18, 1975 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-002. Citizens for Reagan: A Panel Survey of Attitudes of Florida Republicans, February 14, 1976 - February 14, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-002. Citizens for Reagan: A Panel Survey of Attitudes of Florida Republicans, February 14, 1976 - February 14, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-002. Citizens for Reagan: A Panel Survey of Attitudes of Florida Republicans, February 14, 1976 - February 14, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 610-004-005. Citizens for Reagan: A Post-New Hampshire Survey of Republicans in Florida, February 27, 1976 - February 28, 1976 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-001. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Republican Primary Voters in Florida, November 27, 1979 - December 4, 1979 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-001. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Republican Primary Voters in Florida, November 27, 1979 - December 4, 1979 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-002. Reagan for President Committee: A Study of Attitudes of Republican Registered Voters in Florida Wave II, January 3, 1980 - January 4, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-003. Reagan for President Committee: A Panel Survey of Florida Republicans, February 16, 1980 - February 17, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-004. Reagan for President Committee: Florida Tracking, February 29, 1980 - March 9, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-005. Reagan for President Committee: A Statewide Survey of Voters in Florida., June 26, 1980 - June 26, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-006. Reagan/Bush: Florida Statewide - Wave I, August 25, 1980 - August 27, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-007. RNC: Florida Statewide, September 1, 1980 - October 1, 1980 (Box 10)
  - 610-015-007. Reagan/Bush: Florida Statewide - Wave II, September 27, 1980 - October 1, 1980 (Box 11)
  - 610-015-008. RNC: Florida Tracking, October 1, 1980 - November 1, 1980 (Box 11)
  - 610-015-008.: Florida Statewide, October 15, 1980 - October 19, 1980 (Box 11)
  - 610-015-009. Reagan/Bush '84: A Statewide Survey of Florida voters, June 6, 1984 - June 10, 1984 (Box 11)
  - 610-015-010. Reagan/Bush '84: A Statewide Telephone Survey of Voters in Florida, September 8, 1984 - September 10, 1984 (Box 11)
  - 611-008-005. RNC: A Banner Based on Merged 1984-1985 Data, November 1, 1984 - November 1, 1985 (Box 11)
  - 611-008-006. RNC: Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Georgia, September 22, 1986 - September 24, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 611-009-002. Reagan/Bush '84: A Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Georgia, August 30, 1984 - September 1, 1984 (Box 11)
  - 611-009-011. Reagan/Bush '84: A Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Georgia, March 1, 1984 (Box 11)
  - 613-006-001. RNC: Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Idaho, January 7, 1986 - January 8, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 613-006-001. RNC: Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Idaho, January 7, 1986 - January 8, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 613-006-001. RNC: Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Idaho, January 7, 1986 - January 8, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 613-006-001. RNC: Statewide Survey of Registered Voters in Idaho, January 7, 1986 - January 8, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 614-013-001. Citizens for Reagan: A Survey of Republican Voters in Illinois, November 22, 1975 - November 29, 1975 (Box 11)
  - 614-013-001. Citizens for Reagan: A Survey of Republican Voters in Illinois, November 22, 1975 - November 29, 1975 (Box 11)
  - 614-013-002. Citizens for Reagan: A Panel Survey of Republicans in Illinois, January 31, 1976 - January 31, 1976 (Box 11)
  - 614-013-002. Citizens for Reagan: A Panel Survey of Republicans in Illinois, January 31, 1976 - January 31, 1976 (Box 11)
  - 614-013-003. Citizens for Reagan: A Third Survey of Illinois Republicans, March 10, 1976 - March 10, 1976 (Box 12)
  - 614-020-001. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Republican Primary Voters in Illinois, November 1, 1979 - December 1, 1979 (Box 12)
  - 614-020-002. Reagan for President: A Statewide Survey of Republican Primary Voters in Illinois - Wave II, February 9, 1980 - February 10, 1980 (Box 12)
  - 614-020-003. Reagan for President: Illinois Tracking Surveys, March 1, 1980 (Box 12)
  - 614-020-008. Reagan/Bush '84: Illinois Statewide Tracking, September 1, 1984 - September 1, 1984 (Box 12)
  - 614-020-009. Reagan/Bush: Cross sectional Illinois, September 9, 1984 - October 12, 1984 (Box 12)
  - 614-021-001. RNC: A Survey of Voter Attitudes in Illinois 9th Congressional District, September 10, 1980 - September 10, 1980 (Box 12)
  - 614-021-002. RNC: First Illinois Statewide Report from National "Eagle" Surveys I - X, January 1, 1981 - August 14, 1981 (Box 12)